WWW.52HALFCD.COM
时代影视论坛 荣誉出品
影片压制&字幕制作：liubinqing
豆腐脑
Semi-congealed bean curd
好的
Good of
有...
Have...
再来一碗　好
Again come a bowl of good
这味不错
This flavor is quite good
大清光绪二十年（甲午）
Greatly clear out a clue for 20 years(A noon)
（公元一八九四年五月）（夜零时）
(May, 1894)(night zero:00)
左脚滑，右脚蹬空
The left foot is slippery, right foot Deng empty
李中堂？
Hall in Lee?
可不是
Be not
我们派兵朝鲜
We send soldier Korea
去平定东学党之乱
Quell east to learn a disorderly party
日本政府提出抗议说...
The Japanese government put forward to protest against...
日本政府从来未承认
The Japanese government always didn't admit
朝鲜是我们的属邦
Korea is our to belong to a nation
为什么要他们承认
Why to want them to admit
朝鲜根本是箕子的后代
Korea is basically the posterity of Ji son
不但与汉人同文
Not only are of the same language with Hahn people
而且与我们满人同语
And and our full person together language
所以，我看李中堂
So, I see the hall in Lee
就为这件事上朝的
Is this matter up dynasty of
翁同禾跟他可不大对呀
Weng together grain and he isn't big rightness ah
我看朝上有的辨的了
The Bian that I see with an upward exposure have of
（谷峰演李鸿章）
(The valley Feng plays Li Hong Zhang)
（张瑛饰翁同禾）
(Zhang Ying decorates Weng together grain)
（翁同禾是清朝同治、光绪两朝皇帝的老师）
(Weng together grain is the Manchu Dynasty together cures, Guangxu two dynasty emperors of teacher)
寇连材
The Kou connects a material
小小年纪
Small age
又跑到这种地方来干什么？
Run to this kind of place again to dry what?
真不学好
Really not learn like
又来打听皇上跟皇后的事？
Find out the business of emperor and empress again?
昨晚上怎么样？
How about ascending last night?
你没看见吗？
Didn't you see?
还是那句老话，没那八宗事
Or that old words, have no those eight matters
真是，放着河水不洗船
Be really, put river water not to wash a ship
耽误了儿子不要紧
It's unimportant to hold up a son
连孙子都耽误了
Even the grandsons all held up
什么，你说什么？
What, what do you say?
没什么
Nothing important
去...走
Go...Walk
没什么
Nothing important
小兔崽子
Leveret Zai son
去...
Go...
来...
Come...
万岁！万岁！万万岁！
Long live!Long live!Ten thousand long live!
＝＝《倾国倾城》＝＝
==《Extremely beautiful 》==
监制：邵仁枚
Produce:Of Shao Ren
制片：刘子炜　剧务：湿柏南　场记：李振金
Film producer:Liu Zi Wei's play works:The wet cypress south field records:Li Zhen Jin
布景：陈景森　摄影：林　超　灯光：炎　伯
Setting:Chen Jing Zi You Xi Sen photographs:Lin Chao's light:Burning uncle
道具：黎沃　服装：刘季友　化装：吴绪清　梳装：彭姑
Prop:The Li fertile clothing:Liu Ji You's disguise:Wu Xu Qing combs to pack:Peng Gu
剪辑：姜兴隆　录音：王永华
Shear Ji:Prosperous recording:King always China
助导：夏祖辉　马斐
Help to lead:Summer Zu Hui Ma Fei
音乐：陈永煜
Music:Chen always Yu
导演：李翰祥
Direct:Li Han Xiang
字幕制作：依然海天　QQ：2030350
The sub-title creates:Still the sea QQ in the sky:2030350
（苗天饰李莲英）
(The sky of the seedling decorates Li Lian Ying)
老佛爷醒了没有？
Is the old Buddha Ye awake to have no?
还没呢，您先请坐
Didn't°yet, you Please sit down first
老叔
Old uncle
怎么啦，连材，这么哈吃哈吃的？
How, connect a material, admire so to eat admire eat?
（姜大卫饰寇连材）
(David decorates Kou to connect a material)
一口气跑回来的
At a stretch run back
早朝上又提打仗了
Early and with an upward exposure lift to fight again
老佛爷没醒？
Didn't the old Buddha Ye come to?
还睡着呢
Return asleep
怎么又提起来了
How to lift again
老佛爷不是说过
Old Buddha Ye not is once say
不准无事生非吗？
No making trouble out of nothing?
据说朝鲜的事闹大了
It is said that the business of Korea made greatly
日本小鬼趁火打劫死不退兵
Japanese little devil's looting dead doesn't draw back troops
李鸿章没说...
Li Hong Zhang didn't say...
咱们跟小鬼订过约，签过字
We with little devil once order invite, label lead word
可以据约力争的吗？
Can according to work hard for around?
连损带挖苦的
Connect Sun to take sarcasm
李伯爷挨了不少骂呢
Li Bo2 Ye got not a few scold
您说他为什么不愿意打呢？
Why would your saying him not like to beat?
李伯爷眼光远大
Li Bo2 Ye's taste is great
懂得顺从老佛爷的意思
Know the meaning of obeying the old Buddha Ye
这趟到天津检阅水师
This goes to Tienjin to inspect navy
我把老佛爷的意思告诉他不少
I tell him the meaning of the old Buddha Ye not a few
今儿个早朝可有点跟您过不去
Now son early toward canning have a little to can not pass with you
跟我？
Heel I?
说老佛爷尽挑眼，找岔儿
Say the old Buddha Ye to the utmost picks an eye and seek trouble
都是您挑唆出来的
All is that you instigate
那么把我给除了去就好了
So give me in addition to go to good
他怎么说？
How does he say?
醇亲王奏禀
The Chun prince moves to report
去天津检阅水师的经过
Go to the process that Tienjin inspects navy
就是大半天
Is a big along while
接着大臣们上手本
Immediately after big ministers start an origin
本本都是弹劾您的
All of this are to impeach yours
皇上气的不得了
What emperor annoyed is very serious
说不定还要派人来拿你问罪
Perhaps still need to send a person to come to take you denounce and punish
手本上怎么说？
Hand originally up how say?
我在屏风后面听不大清楚
I behind listen to not greatly clear in the screen
总不外说的是您是内廷的总管
Always not and outside what to say is you is inside the manager of court
怎么干涉起外廷的朝政
How to start to interfere with the domestic affairs of outside court
显然是犯了什么...
Obviously made what...
对，‘千月’‘千月’之罪
To, 'thousand months''thousand months'of offense
‘千月’‘千月’是什么东西？
'Thousand months''thousand months'is what things?
谁知道他们什么‘千月’‘百月’的
Who know them what'thousand months''100 months'of
反正您的罪可不轻
Anyway your offense isn't light
您想想一千个月可得多少年
You want can get many youths for 1,000 months
他们说的是“僣越”之罪
They say of is the offense of "the 僣 is more"
僣越？
Is the 僣 more?
什么叫僣越？
What call 僣 more?
这一帮猴崽子
This helps the monkey Zai the son
嫌咱们的脚步迈多了一步
The footstep that dislikes us exceeds many one step
跨出了门槛
Across threshold
（沈劳饰王商）
(Chen2 Lao2 decorates Wang Shang)
李总管在不在？
Manager Lee at not at?
王大叔他在不在呀？
Wang Da Dun Shu at not at ah?
您瞧，可不是真来了吗？
Your lo, be not really come?
听嗓门儿好像是王商
Listen to the voice son seeming Wang Shang
去看看去
See
喳
Zha
谁呀？
Who ah?
喳
Zha
奴才李莲英一大早
Slave Li Lian Ying is in early morning
给您请早安来了
Invite good-morning for you
愿老佛爷您福寿无疆
It's limitless to wish old Buddha Ye your blessing life
万岁！万岁！万万岁！
Long live!Long live!Ten thousand long live!
是你呀，什么时候回来的？
Is you ah, when come back?
昨晚上夜车回来的
The car came back last night last night
都大半夜了
All greater half night
怕惊动您老佛爷的大驾
Afraid disturb your your good self of old Buddha Ye
没敢来给您请安
Have never dared to come to send greeting for you
多早晚了？
Much sooner or later?
老阳都上了宝座了
The old sun all ascended throne
您垂廉的功夫
You hang the effort of Lian
恐怕这时候早朝都要散了
Perhaps and by this time and early toward all wanting to spread
如今养老了
Retire to enjoy life now
您慢慢儿地起动起动吧
You slowly the son ground start
这殿里又是佛手又是藏香
This palace inside again is a Buddha's hand again is hide joss-stick
还有那么多的大牡丹花
Still have so many big peony flowers
都争着放香儿呢，您呐
All emulate to put fragrant son, you shout
我就起
I rise
传御膳房给您预备早膳吧？
Spread to resist food building to prepare breakfast for you?
好吧
All right
喳
Zha
其实也没什么大不了的
In fact also no big deal
大概是皇上想跟李总管打听打听
Probably is an emperor to want to find out pry with manager Lee
海军的情形
The navy's situation
传膳
Spread a food
喳
Zha
李总管早晨好
Manager Lee morning good
我当是谁讨了这份好差事
I am is who begged for this good work
原来是王商王大太监
Is the big eunuch of Wang Shang Wang
总管，您别见怪
Manager, you don't be offended
皇上的旨意，没法子啊
The emperor's aim idea has no idea
是啊，皇上的旨意
Yes, the emperor's aim idea
如今皇上听了政
The emperor listenned to a government now
一朝天子一朝臣
One dynasty Emperor one courtier
皇上的左右手
The emperor's left and right hands
都挺起腰板儿来了
All start to stand waist plank the son came
王商不敢
Wang Shang doesn't dare
王商还是李总管台爱
Wang Shang still the set love of manager Lee
派去伺候皇上的
The parties waits upon an emperor
可是现在反过来倒咬一口
But turn over to pour to give a bite now
奴才不敢
The slave doesn't dare
奴才是小人，能作什么主
The slave is a mean person and can do what lord
皇上指派奴才怎么着
The emperor names slave how wear
奴才就怎么着
Slave how wear
李总管指派小的怎么回话
Manager Lee names small of how message of reply
小的还不就怎么回话
Smallly still not how message of reply
好，你去回话
Like, you go to message of reply
就说李总管在伺候太后老佛爷
Say manager Lee at waits upon the queen mother old Buddha Ye
没功夫
Have no an effort
喳
Zha
小的回去，看皇上怎么发落
Smallly return to, see an emperor how to dispose of
要骂小的一顿
Want to scold smallly
说这么点差事你都办不下来
Say that order so work, you don't to come down
小的还说不定得回来
Smallly still perhaps must come back
那得求您赏个脸跟小的走一趟
That must beg you to appreciate a face heel to smallly make a trip
别皇上说往东，您说往西
Don't emperor say eastwards, you say westwards
那小的可就为难，不知那头去好了
That smallly can difficult, not know that to go to
还有你说的
Still have what you say
您多包涵
You much forgive
忘本
Ungrateful
不是您派他去伺候皇上的吗？
Isn't that you send does he wait upon an emperor?
可不是嘛
Be not
连材
Connect a material
喳
Zha
我派你一个好差事
I send your[one] good work
你去伺候皇上好吗？
You wait upon an emperor good?
那敢情好，您多栽培
That dare feeling good, you much educate
你十几了？
You ten Be getting more several?
今年十七，前年进宫的
This year 17, the before last year enter temple of
我派你去伺候皇上
I send you wait upon an emperor
要伺候的很周密
Want to wait upon of very careful and attentive
要寸步不离
Want to be closely
他的一举一动都要随时报告给我
His each and every moves all want to report to me at any time
懂吗？
Understand?
懂，我这一去，不就盯上他了吗
Understand, I this goes, didn't stare at to ascend him
他说什么做什么
What does he say to do what
甭想逃过我的眼睛
Don't want to once escape my eyes
好，你跟他去看看
Like, you see with him
喳
Zha
老佛爷吉祥平安，您早晨好
Old Buddha Ye the good luck is peaceful, you morning good
告诉他们
Tell them
我在伺候太后老佛爷的，没空去
I at wait upon the queen mother old Buddha Ye of, have no time
什么事呀？
What matter ah?
莲英，进来
Lotus English comes in
喳
Zha
太后老佛爷救命
The queen mother old Buddha Ye Helps
奴才该死，一回来就给您添麻烦
The slave damns and trouble you on coming back
又怎么了？
How again?
有人到太后老佛爷的寝宫来
Someone arrives the bedchamber of the queen mother old Buddha Ye
捉拿您的奴才来了
The slave that arrests you came
这么大胆子，谁呀？
So bold son, who ah?
光绪爷，万岁爷(卢燕饰慈喜太后)
Guangxu Ye, long live Ye(Lu Yan decorates the Ci pleased queen mother)
他，为什么？
He, why?
有大臣上奏，弹劾奴才
There is a big minister up moving, impeach slave
说不该代替老佛爷到天津去
Saying should not replace old Buddha Ye to go to Tienjin
瞧，把我们的总管吓得这样
Lo frightens our managers so
起来吧，有我呢
Get up and have me
原来是这么芝麻大点的事
The matter that originally is so a sesame to greatly order
瞧，梳得像乱草似的
Lo, comb be like disorderly grass
起来给我梳头，他们老梳不好
The getting up combs hair for me, they are old to comb not good
喳
Zha
瞧你吓得这样
Lo you frighten so
你就这么怕皇上？
You so afraid emperor?
太后撤廉归政以后
The queen mother withdraws Lian to return a government hereafter
大权都由光绪爷在握
Big power all from the Ye in control in Guangxu
咱们仪栾殿的就算是退休了
Our instrument Luan palace of at last retire
奴才处处退步
The slave retrogresses in everywhere
可是他们，您瞧
But they, your lo
一直逼到寝宫来了
Make the bedchamber come
这叫奴才怎么能不害怕
This calls the slave to how to not fear
你说的咱们就这么没面子？
You say of do we have no so a face?
老佛爷，您这一撤廉不要紧
Old Buddha Ye, you this withdraws Lian unimportant
就连我们做奴才的
Connect we do slave
都不敢大声吭气儿了
All don't dare to loudly utter spirit son
打狗还得看主人嘛
Beating the dog still have to see host
跟奴才们过不去
Can not pass with the slaves
不也就是跟太后老佛爷您过不去
Not is also and the queen mother old Buddha Ye you can not pass
他怎么会跟你们做奴才过不去呢
Does he how can do slave to can not pass with you
他从小就是这个脾气
He was this temper since the childhood
你又不是不知道
You again be not don't know
不会的，怎么会呢
Can't of, how can
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
都这时候了，早朝还没散
All by this time, the dynasty early hasn't spread
听说又计划着跟日本人开战呢
It is said that planning to open hostilities with Japanese again
怎么，旧病又复发了？
How, did the old disease again deliver?
皇上忘记了
The emperor forgot
今年是您六旬大庆的好日子
This year is your nice day of six Xun Ta-chings
颐和园的工程就等着油漆彩画
The engineering of Summer Palace waits to varnish a colourful painting
眼看着就要完工了
See Be about to complete work
这孩子，我告诉他别乱来
This kid, I tell him to make a mess of
这么大了，还让我操心
So big, also make me worry
也难怪，东洋人是欺负人
Also no wonder that, Japan the person is to humiliate a person
亲政不久，年轻人想有一番作为
Close government soon, the young man wants to have to be some kind of Be
也不是一件坏事
BE not a bad matter either
只要不太离格儿
Want ～only to not too leave space son
皇上想有所作为，当然不是坏事
The emperor wants to have Be, the of course not is a bad matter
只是太年轻了点
Just too a little bit young
自己又没有准稿子
Oneself has no quasi- draft again
大臣们就胡言乱语地尽出花招
Big ministers talk wildly ground to exert the flower recruit
皇上哪禁得起他们的挑唆
Emperor which can stand their to instigate
依奴才看
See according to slave
老佛爷您还不能躲心静儿
Old Buddha Ye you can not also hide the heart quiet son
您还得多操持操持
You still have to much hold to hold to hold to hold
老了，懒得操这份闲心
Be getting older, lazy must hold this a free mind
奴才寇连材请太后老佛爷您早安
The slave Kou connects a material to invite your good-morning of old Buddha Ye of queen mother
愿太后老佛爷福寿无疆
It's limitless to wish the queen mother old Buddha Ye blessing life
万岁，万岁，万万岁
Long live, long live, ten thousand long live
起来吧
Get up
谢太后老佛爷
Thank the queen mother old Buddha Ye
他们呢，都走了？
What about them and all walked?
又回来了
Come back again
死说活说，说了半天就是不肯走
The dead says that live to say, said that the along while is to be not willing to walk
要您立刻去呢
Want you to immediately go
告诉他们说老佛爷生气了
Tell them to say the old Buddha Ye is angry
谁借他们的胆子
Who lend him of courage
敢到仪栾殿来抓总管太监
Dare to arrive instrument Luan palace to grasp manager eunuch
有什么事叫皇上自己来说
Have what matter to call the emperor to say by himself[herself]
领旨
Get an aim
还得了
Still have to
喳
Zha
连材
Connect a material
喳
Zha
你看早朝散了没有
You see early toward spreading to have no
打仗的事再去打听打听
Matter of fighting then find out pry
喳
Zha
太后作主，奴才谢恩
The queen mother makes the decision, the slave thanks for favor
起来吧，梳头要紧
Get up and comb hair important
已经梳好了
Have already combed
梳好了？
Comb?
我瞧瞧
My lo lo
可不是嘛，又麻利又好
Be not, again tingle benefit again good
没一袋烟的工夫就服服贴贴
It's very loving and obedient to have no the time of a bag of smoke
你们学点乖
You learn to order lovely
一个个笨手笨脚的
An is clumsy
难怪作不了总管
No wonder that can not make manager
老佛爷，您又拿奴才开心了
Old Buddha Ye, you take slave again happy
又不是一天半天
Isn't a day again along while
伺候您几十年了
Wait upon you for several decades
老佛爷，您用膳吧
Old Buddha Ye, you take meal
好吧
All right
皇上
Emperor
这是什么？
What is this ?
宫门钱，给李总管的
Money in the temple door gives manager Lee
是常规，每天都有的
Is a normal regulations, have every day
我怎么不知道？
How don't I know?
您不知道的事还多着呢
Is the matter that you don't know and the rise
皇上
Emperor
起来...我不需要这一套
Get up...I don't need to be this set of
喳
Zha
太后呢？
What about queen mother?
老佛爷正用早膳，就出来
The old Buddha Ye is using breakfast, come out
皇上，娘娘在那边
Your Majesty, the empress is over there
看见了
See
她的贵恙还没十分复原呢
Hasn't her expensive Yang pretty much recovered
您看她的脸色
You see her facial expression
比前两天顺亮多了吧
Compare fluently much brighter two days ago
（凌波饰皇后）
(Ling Po decorates an empress)
连材
Connect a material
喳
Zha
你替我去禀太后
You report queen mother for me
说我给他问早安来了
Say I ask good-morning for him
身子不支，先回去了
The body cans not stand up and returned to first
喳
Zha
娘娘
Empress
您不要紧吧
You are unimportant
那您多坐一会儿
That you much sit in a short while
刚才老佛爷还惦念您来着
The just old Buddha Ye still remembers you come
要不然您两位多谈谈
Otherwise you 2 much discuss
我去给您回禀
I go to and report back for you
知道你没把我放在心上
The knowing you didn't put me in the mind
你今天是怎么啦？
You today is how?
你故意跟我起哄是怎么着？
Your intentionally creating a big noise with me is to how wear?
你不是不理我吗？
You not is ignore me?
皇上
Emperor
我今天...
I am today...
叩见皇上、皇后
Pay visit to an emperor, empress
皇上跟皇后...在说话了
Emperor and empress...At talk
说话呢
Talk
要嫌奴才们礙眼，奴才们就...
The slaves to dislike the slaves 礙 eye...
有什么怕你们听的
Have what afraid that you listen to
没什么，已经说完了
Nothing important has already said finishing
李莲英
Li Lian Ying
喳
Zha
早上我派王商找你上殿问话
My parties Wang Shang seeks your last palace to ask words in the morning
你怎么...
You how...
奴才很对不起皇上
Slave very sorry emperor
不是奴才不去
Isn't a slave don't go
实在是奴才一派出去就是大半个月
Really is a slave one parties go out be greater half month
如今一回来，奴才的事情特别多
On coming back now, the affair of slave is specially many
尤其是伺候太后，老佛爷的差事
Particularly wait upon queen mother, the work of old Buddha Ye
奴才...
Slave...
算了
Forget it
哪来这么多“奴才”“奴才”的
Where to come to so many"slave"s"slave"s
我问你，这次你...
I ask you, this time you...
皇上请稍候
Emperor wait for a while, please
娘娘
Empress
太后请您里边说话
The queen mother invites you the inside talk
皇上请留步，太后没旨
The emperor stops sending off, the queen mother has no an aim
我有急事
I have urgent matter
这是礼儿，这是规矩
This is the gift son, this is the rules
李莲英
Li Lian Ying
你也慢点进去，过来
You are also slowly to go in and come over
皇上有什么吩咐？
What order does the emperor have?
有什么吩咐？
What order?
我问你知罪不知罪？
Do I ask you to know that the offense doesn't know offense?
奴才不知道犯了什么罪
The slave didn't know to make what offense
你呀，你就是贪污的那个根儿
You ah, you are the root son of corruption
奴才不懂，您...
The slave doesn't understand, you...
您甭装傻
You don't pretend ignorance
奴才随醇亲王到天津
The slave gets to Tienjin with the Chun prince
是老佛爷指派
Is an old Buddha Ye to name
皇上您恩准的
The emperor is approved
是啊，有人弹劾你这一点
Yes, someone impeaches you this
我都说过去了
I said passing by
可是还有呢
But still have
还有？
Still have?
奴才就不得而知了
The slave canned not know
奴才当差，从来不敢僣越一步
The slave is bad, never dare the 僣 is more one-step
就是立下了不少新规矩，臭规矩
Be sign next not a few new ruleses, smelly rules
贪污的规矩
The rules of corruption
皇上
Emperor
奴才该死，奴才敢立什么规矩
The slave damns, the slave dares to sign what rules
什么都是列祖列宗的成法
What is all becoming of forbears method
皇上虽然是亲政不久
Although the emperor is soon close government
可从四岁起在宫里长大
Can from 4 years old rise in the temple to grow up
什么礼法都看见过了
What gift the methods all once saw
从小时候起，从奴才抱着皇上
Since childhood, embrace an emperor from the slave
拉着皇上的手儿上殿起
Pull the emperor's hand son last palace to rise
住口
Shut up
我现在已经长大了
I have already grown up now
喳
Zha
你还抖我的根子，欺负我小吗？
You still tremble my root son, humiliate me small?
奴才不敢
The slave doesn't dare
你以为我只懂玩
You think my understands to have fun
什么都不懂啊
Don't understand anything
奴才不敢
The slave doesn't dare
这内廷里的宫门费
This inside fee in the temple door of court inside
今儿个我差点都进不来
Now son I almost all enter not come
是不是你兴的？
Isn't that you are cheerful?
奴才不敢
The slave doesn't dare
这次你到天津去检阅海军
You go to Tienjin to inspect navy this time
一路之上无论大小官府
All the way on regardless all of the authorities
尤其与海军有关系的衙门
Particularly and navy relational Ya door
点着名、数着数儿要贿赂
Ordering is well-known and count to count son to want hush money
是不是你兴的
Isn't that you are cheerful
奴才不敢
The slave doesn't dare
别老‘不敢’‘不敢’的
Don't be old'not dare''do not dare'of
我问你，是不是你兴的？
Do I ask you, isn't that you are cheerful?
奴才不敢
The slave doesn't dare
我问你，你知不知罪？
I ask you, do you know offense?
说，你知不知罪？
Say, do you know offense?
奴才是不敢嘛
The slave is to don't dare
你怎么老是不敢不敢的
You how always don't dare don't dare
奴才真的不敢
The slave really doesn't dare
不敢...
Don't dare...
别以为你伺候太后，是大总管
Don't think you wait upon queen mother, is a big manager
就可以为非作歹，无恶不作
Can carry on misdeed, do every evils
请皇上开恩，奴才实在是不敢
Please grand pardon, the slave really doesn't dare
你的胆子是越来越大了
You of the courage was more and more big
你的眼睛里根本没有我这个皇上
Your eyes inside basically has no my this emperor
我派王商传你上殿
I send Wang Shang to spread your last palace
你竟敢抗旨不遵
You unexpectedly dare anti- aim not Zun
那是因为太后老佛爷她这边的事...
That because queen mother old Buddha Ye her business...
别又老佛爷，太后老佛爷
Don't again old Buddha Ye, the queen mother old Buddha Ye
真是老佛爷
Is really an old Buddha Ye
确是老佛爷吗？
Is an indeed old Buddha Ye?
什么事啊？
What matter?
真是老佛爷，确是老佛爷的
Being really an old Buddha Ye is an indeed old Buddha Ye
亲爸爸，吉祥平安，您早晨好
In person father, the good luck is peaceful, you morning good
好倒是好，就是不大平安
It is good to pour so much, isn't big peaceful
怎么一大早
How in early morning
就到我寝宫抓起人来了
Is my bedchamber to catch a person to come
我怎么敢呢，我不过去问问他
I how dare, I however ask
因为上早朝有人上折子弹劾他
Because the top early folds son to impeach him toward someone
他犯了什么罪啊？
He made what offense?
随醇亲王检阅海军
Inspect navy with the Chun prince
恐蹈唐朝监军覆辙
Perhaps the Dao tang dynasty Jian soldier replies Zhe
那是我派的
That is what I send
是，我也准了的
BE, I am also getting more quasi-
那不就结了吗？
Doesn't that knot?
可一路上
All the way last
有少告他贪财纳贿的状子
Have the plaint to tell his money-mad Na Hui less
他有没有呢？
Does he have?
我正问他，他已经没话说了
I am asking him, he has already had no words to say
您看
You see
李莲英
Li Lian Ying
喳
Zha
你是一路上撒网打秋风受贿赂了
You is all the way and up cast net to beat autumnal winds is bribed
奴才不敢
The slave doesn't dare
到底有没有？
Exactly have?
太后老佛爷，您圣明
The queen mother old Buddha Ye, your saint is clear
奴才随醇亲王到天津检阅水师
The slave goes to Tienjin to inspect navy with the Chun prince
是朝廷特派的钦差
Is the imperial envoy that the imperial government appoints especially
也是代替太后跟皇上的
Is also replace queen mother and emperor
一路所到之处
All the way arrive of place
不论大小衙门无不欢迎恭送
In spite of the size Ya door all welcomes to send respectfullly
也是欢迎恭送太后跟皇上
Is also welcome to send queen mother and emperor respectfullly
临别呢人家贡献点当地的土产
Facing don't somebody else's contribution order the local product of the region
也是人之常情
Is also a common feeling
人家一片好心，咱们也不便谢绝
Somebody else one good heart, we are also inconvenient to decline
多少人忌妒奴才这档子好差事
How much person envy slave this file son good work
就编派奴才些
Libel slave some
什么贪赃受贿这些话
What be greedy for Zang to take bribe these words
还请太后老佛爷跟皇上您明鉴
Still invite old Buddha Ye of queen mother heel emperor your clear example of history
我看也许有的
I see probably have
亲爸爸，您不知道
In person father, you don't know
人家告他有眉有眼的
The somebody else tells he has eyebrow to have an eye
说他点着名儿
Say he orders well-known son
数着数儿的向人张手
Count number son of open hand toward the person
算了，你也没看见
Calculate, you didn't also see
欲加之罪，何患无辞呢
The offense that the desire adds, what suffer from having no Ci
那些人妒忌他，小心眼儿
Those people envy him, narrow-minded
也难为他一路上辛苦
Also difficult is that he ascends a pain all the way
算了，你先起来
Calculate, you got up first
是
BE
亲爸爸，我是想杀一儆百
In person father, I am to want to kill one as a warning to a hundred
想整一整这贪污的风气
Want to fix hash the custom of this corruption
当然好，可是你别打我们这边来呀
Certainly good, but you don't beat we come
李伯爷
Li Bo2 Ye
从同治年间起
From together cure an in year to rise
我们就连年开矿山，办工厂
We for successive years open mines mountain and do factory
筑码头，修铁道
Build wharf, fix railroad
设武备学堂，立海军衙门
Establish Wu Bei's schools, sign navy Ya door
买机器，添枪炮，可是...
Buy machine, add arms and supplies, but...
而到今天国家有事，要用了
But occupy to today's nation, use
怎么样啊？
How?
皇上，凡是有办洋务不利的地方
Your Majesty, every have the place to do ocean duty disadvantage
都是臣的疏忽
Is all negligence of minister
这次不能跟日本动兵
Can not dispatch troops to fight with Japan this time
也是臣的过失，可是...
Is also the mistake of minister, but...
臣也有难言之隐
The minister also has concealed difficult speech
你说
You say
左右人多，恐怕不便
The or so person is many and afraid of inconvenience
连材
Connect a material
喳
Zha
你...你站在这儿干什么？
You...You stand here do what?
我...我倒茶
I...I pour tea
倒好了？
Pour?
倒好了
Pour
那么下去
So descend to go to
奴才正听得出神
The slave is listenning to appear lost in thought
想他们两位谁的理儿对
Miss their two whoseses manage a son rightness
你先出去一趟吧
You go out 1 first
不
Not
皇上，正说在要紧的结股眼上
The Your Majesty is saying the eye is at the important knot up
您也让奴才多懂点
You also make the slave understood point more
我求你到后边去待一会儿吧
I beg you to the back to treat in a short while
喳
Zha
你指的是太后？
You point of is a queen mother?
太后，和太后一党的王公大臣
Queen mother, and the dukes and high ministers of queen mother one party
比方醇亲王他老人家主持军机
For instance Chun prince his old man's house manages a military airplane
竟连一点主意也不敢有
Unexpectedly connect some idea don't dare to have as well
太后说什么是什么
What does queen mother say to is what
满朝文武谁敢得罪太后
Full dynasty text force who dare to give offense to queen mother
在内有总管太监李莲英
At inside have the manager eunuch Li Lian Ying
在外有军机大臣孙毓汶
There is big military airplane in the outside minister Sun Yu Wen
内外呼应，他们都是太后的耳目
Inside the outside act in cooperation, all of them are the ear eyes of queen mother
太后明是归政养老了
Queen mother's being clear is to return a government to retire to enjoy life
实际还隐隐地握着大权呢
Physically still unclearly hold big power
臣倒想起来了
The minister poured to think of
编修文廷式等
Edit type in the text court to wait
屡次奏请起用恭亲王
Frequently move to start to please to use respectful prince
恭亲王曾受过文宗的遗诏
The respectful prince once was subjected to a text to believe in of loosed Zhao
让他节制太后
Let him forbear queen mother
所以，太后别人不怕
So, queen mother the other people aren't afraid
见他倒有点顾忌
See him pouring to a little bit have scruples about
可是太后会肯么？
But queen mother meeting be willing to?
太后对恭亲王一向敬而远之
Queen mother to respectful prince always respect but far it
本朝十一年
This dynasty is 11 years
跟法国在安南的战争一起
Heel France at Annamese of the war is together
他老人家就被罢官了
He old man's house was resigned from office
一直住闲到现在
Have been living carefree till now
恭亲王还有一股正气还激烈
The respectful prince still has a sense of right to return vehemence
皇上...
Emperor...
今天就算恭亲王出来
Today calculate the respectful prince come out
我们谁能，谁敢...
We who ability, who dare...
请太后不修园子，不庆寿
Please don't fix garden, don't celebrate birthday
皇上
Emperor
我
I
寇太监在隔壁
The Kou eunuch is in the next door
你都听见了
You heard
是
BE
连材，你怎么会偷听？
Connect a material, do you how can eavesdrop?
这关系太大了
This relation is a lot too big
你千万可不能够说出去啊
You must can not tell others
这关系皇上和臣子的性命
This life that relates to emperor and minister son
你...莫不是有人派你来的？
You...Someone could it be that send do you come?
你是来做眼线，是来当密探的？
You is to do informer, is to be spy?
是不是？快说
BE be not?Say quickly
寇太监是不是？说呀你
Kou eunuch is be not?Say ah you
说，你说
Say, you say
是不是，说啊...
BE be not, say...
是，奴才是被派来做眼线
BE, the slave is been sent to do informer
做密探的
Do spy
皇上，您放心
Your Majesty, you trust
来，是他们派我来的，可是...
Coming is what they send me come, but...
你不能卖主子
You not ability seller son
奴才知道，奴才都知道
The slave knows that the slaves all know
连材有天良，不会卖主子的
Connect a material to contain conscience, can't seller son of
那就好，你先起来吧
That good, you get up first
现在我明白过来了
I was understand to come over now
瞧吧，没有人劝太后
Lo, no one advises queen mother
我去劝
I advise
寇太监...
Kou eunuch...
连材，你不能去
Connect a material, you can not go
皇上，您放心
Your Majesty, you trust
寇太监...
Kou eunuch...
怎么得了...
How will all this end...
第一个李姐儿
The first girls Lee
第二第三两个是翁师傅推许的
The second is two or three is teacher Weng to push to allow
长敘的两个女儿，是姐妹两个
Two daughters who grow 敘 are two sisters
还有两个呢？
There are also 2?
也是亲姐妹
Is also a close sister
是江西总督德馨的两个女儿
Is two daughters of virtuous river west governor of province Xin
好，等皇上办好了
Like, wait an emperor to do
我们把她们送到毓庆宫去
We send to the Yu to them and celebrate a temple
让他自个再选
Let him choose again from
连材
Connect a material
我们打胜仗了
We won war
奴才给皇上道喜
The slave congratulates for emperor
我们正式跟他们宣战了
We formally declared war with them
您别打奴才呀
You don't beat slave
从此咱们翻身了
From now on we turned over a body
皇上您这么高兴啊
The emperor is so happy
当然高兴了
Certainly happy
小声点儿
The small voice orders son
太后、皇后跟候选的妃子
The imperial concubine of queen mother, empress and candidate for election
都在套间里边用点心呢
All is the inside used a dessert between each set
她们都来了？
Did they all come?
送上门儿给您选呐
Send to come son to choose for you to shout
您倒是选谁？
Your pouring is to choose who?
你猜？
Do you guess?
当然是李大姐儿哪
Certainly is elder sister Lee's son which
李大姐...
Elder sister Lee...
皇上选妃李大姐
The emperor chooses imperial concubine's elder sister Lee
愿打还是愿罚？
Wish to beat or wish to punish?
你说
You say
愿打怎么打？愿罚怎么罚呢？
Does the wish beat how to beat?Does the wish punish how to punish?
愿打，把裤子脱下来
The wish beats and strip off pants
不行，不可以...
Don't go, can not...
你反正跑不了
You anyway can not run
皇上
Emperor
皇上，您这是干什么？
Your Majesty, you what is this a stem?
我们在试验
We at experiment
据说一个亡国奴就这样跪着
It is said that a Wu country Nu kneels like this
被人骑在背上
BE ridden in carrying on the back
不叫他起来，他不敢起来呢
Don't call him to get up, doesn't he dare
起来吧
Get up
喳
Zha
皇上，您得时时刻刻记得
Your Majesty, you must remember moment by moment
您是皇上
You are an emperor
连材
Connect a material
喳
Zha
太后在里间吗？
Queen mother at in?
是
BE
皇上，皇上怎么样？
Your Majesty, emperor how?
皇上就不准笑笑
The emperor prohibits to smile
皇上就不许玩玩
The emperor forbids to play
皇上就不吃饭
The emperor doesn't have a meal
皇上就不拉屎
The emperor doesn't move bowels
皇上就不是人哪
The emperor isn't a person which
得了，这点小事
Get, this small matter
您不必跟他一般见识
You need not hold the same kind of view with him
他什么时候进来的？
Does he when come in?
奴才也不知道
The slave doesn't know as well
亲爸爸
In person father
我们娘儿们都在等你
Our Niang son all at wait you
你回来了，怎么也不进来呀？
You came back, how didn't come in as well?
我在等翁师傅跟李伯爷
I at wait teacher Weng and Li Bo2 Ye
等他们来了一块儿去见您
Wait they come to together see you
听说你高兴得很呐
It is said that you are happy to shout very much
是啊，亲爸爸，您不高兴吗？
Yes, in person father, aren't you happy?
当然也高兴
Certainly also happy
不过高兴也要有个分寸
However happy also not exceed limits
别太离格儿
Don't leave space son too much
是
BE
我知道今天你又是选妃
I know today you again is choose an imperial concubine
又是胜仗当然高兴
Is that the victorious battle is certainly happy again
对了，亲爸爸
To, in person father
来，告诉亲爸爸
Come, tell close father
你选哪一个？
Which do you choose?
刚才你要是多待一会儿
Just you if much treat in a short while
就可以定了
Can settle
现在剩下她们三个
Leave their 3 now
你说，你喜欢哪一个？
Do you say which you like?
怎么样，你喜欢哪一个？
How, which do you like?
你喜欢哪一个？
Which do you like?
好...
Good...
我是说...她们都好
I am to say...They are all good
我倒是也想都把她们留下
My pouring is to also want to all leave them
现下三宫六院、七十二妃
Now three temples six hospitals and 72 imperial concubines
不时兴了
Often interest
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
其实都留下，三个也不算多
All in fact leave, 3 don't calculate as well much
李莲英的妹子也很好
Li Lian Ying's younger sister's son is also very good
好是好
Is good so much
不过，‘满不点元，汉不选妃’
However, 'full not point dollar, the man doesn't choose an imperial concubine'
奴才已经投了旗啦
The slave has already thrown ensign
投旗...？
Throw ensign...?
投旗终归是投旗
Throw ensign in the end is throw ensign
怕在朝在野的都要说话
Afraid that all wanting of party in government's not in power talks
好吧
All right
奴才还是巴结不上
The slave still fawns on not and up
谁让你是半路出家呢
Who allow you to are a house halfway
没关系，让她跟着我
It doesn't matter, let her follow me
我错待不了她
I am wrong to treat her
谢老佛爷
Thank old Buddha Ye
那么还有那两个呢？
So there are also those 2?
亲爸爸，您给我选吧
In person father, you choose for me
我怕你是花多眼乱
I am afraid that you are to spend many eyes in disorder
这样吧，两姐妹都留下
So, two sisters all leave
互相作伴，也有个照应
Company each other, looks after
好不好？
Not very good?
皇上
Emperor
皇上，中日宣战诏书已经写好了
Your Majesty, wins a day to declare war an imperial enactment have already written
我不赞成宣战
I don't approve to declare war
亲爸爸
In person father
把那个给我
Give me that
放着好好日子不过，打仗！...
Put a very nice day however, fight!...
打仗...打...打呀...
Fight...Beat...Beat...
反不了你
Anti- not you
难得我今儿高兴了一早上
Rare I now the son is happy for a morning
又来呕我
Come to Ou again I
老佛爷起驾了
Old Buddha Ye drove
什么事？猛张飞似的？
What matter?The fierce piece flies?
启禀老佛爷
The Qi reports old Buddha Ye
日本国对我们发宣战诏书了
The Japanese country declared war an imperial enactment to our hair
真的？
Really?
亲爸爸
In person father
都跟我作对...
All set against with me...
没想到...
Unexpectedly...
什么没想到？
What have never thought?
这回可中了你的意罗
Idea Luo who this time can win you
非打仗不可啦
Doing not  fight can not
亲爸爸，现下迫不得已了
In person father, have no alternative now
起用恭亲王的事
Rise the business of using the respectful prince
您也一块答应了吧
You also a cake of promised
别的我不管
Another of I ignore
你们爱怎么着就怎么着
Your love how wear how wear
你们一边打一边想着
You are beating and thinking
十月已经不远了，要早早地了事
No longer Be getting farer in October, early and early settle a dispute
李鸿章
Li Hong Zhang
臣
Minister
有没有办法？
Have a way?
臣这次再去找俄国使臣喀希尼
The minister seeks Russia again to make the minister Ka rare Ni this time
他曾答应过臣
He once promised minister
中日有事
The medium day occupies
他一定帮助中国从中调解
He definitely helps China from the medium intermediation
对了，让他解和解和说句公平话
To, make his solution reached agreement and say a fair words
是，老佛爷
BE, old Buddha Ye
恭亲王爷到了
The respectful prince Ye arrived
快请上来
Will please quickly to come up
他在外面等了一会，说你在收礼
He waited a short while in the outside and said you at accept a gift
他到养心殿去了
He to cultivate mental calm a palace to go
今天风太大，没放轿廉子吗？
The breeze is too strong today, didn't put the son of Jiao Lian?
放了，老年人禁不住
Put, the old people forbade not to live
（郝履仁饰恭亲王）
(The Hao Lyu Ren decorates respectful prince)
真是又害您老人家跑一趟
Be really cause your old man's house to run again 1
说什么？
Say what?
这么大风，又害您老人家跑一趟
So strong wind, and then cause your old man's house to run 1
不要紧
Unimportant
您躺一会好不好
You lie a short while not very good
不要脱，冷啊
Don't take off, cold
老祖宗，您喝杯热茶吧
Old ancestor, you drink the cup hot tea
您也来参加演礼啊
You also take part in to play a gift
是啊
Yes
等了半天，人支持不住啦
Waited along while, the person supported not to live
等谁？
Wait who?
李莲英
Li Lian Ying
他在忙着收礼儿
He at is busy in accepting gift son
好多王公贝勒都等着他
A lot of princes and dukes shell Leis all wait him
我看老祖宗，实在是支持不住了
I see old ancestor, really support not to live
带他到这儿来歇一会
Take he arrives to come to Xie a short while here
说什么？
Say what?
他说您一会儿还要去演礼呐
He says you to in a short while still want to play a gift to shout
演礼？
Play a gift?
老祖宗，您歇一会儿吧
Old ancestor, your Xie is in a short while
老祖宗，您先歇会吧
Old ancestor, you first Xie meeting
不...
Not...
刚才不是说朝鲜已经丢了
Just not is say that Korea has already thrown
关外都保不住了
The pass all outside canned not guarantee
皇上可有什么办法吗
What way can the emperor have
有什么妥善的主意没有啊
Have what appropriate idea have no
您先歇会吧
You first Xie meeting
不...
Not...
皇上要是有什么计议，尽管去办
If the emperor has what account an argument, though do
出了什么事来问我，有我
What matter to ask me, have me
只要我还有这口气儿
Want ～only me to still have this tone son
我就拿这个老命跟她拼了
I took this old life to put together with her
老祖宗...
Old ancestor...
这个女人说怕，当然不会怕我
This woman says it's afraid, certainly can't fear me
可是她多少总有点顾忌吧
But she how much always a little bit have scruples about
皇上，该怎么办就怎么办
Your Majesty, how should do how do
该赏的赏，该罚的罚
Should appreciate of appreciate, should punish of punish
可不能再姑息了
Can not appease again
头一个军机大臣孙毓汶按兵不动
First one military airplane big minister Sun Yu Wen presses the soldier motionless
罢免他
Recall him
能吗？
Ability?
怕什么，我跟太后去说
Afraid of, I say with queen mother
那真太好了
That really too good
还有南方各省一个兵都没出
Still have south each save a soldiers to all have no
就北洋一支军队在打
North ocean a troops at beat
而李鸿章的海军
But Li Hong Zhang's navy
又守在家门口不肯出去
Again guard at family Be not willing to go out
好了...不要说了
Good...Don't say
大清真到了败家的时候了
The big Islamic arrived wasteful of time
现在幸亏还有你懂事
It's reasonable to luckily still have you now
好好地干吧！全看你的了
Well dry!All see you of
祖宗三百年的天下呀
World of ancestor 300 years
老祖宗，您歇会吧
Old ancestor, your Xie meeting
还是那句话
Or that sentence
皇上有什么计议，尽管去办
The emperor has what account an argument, though do
出了什么事
What matter
有我
Have me
老祖宗
Old ancestor
老祖宗，您要躺会吧
Old ancestor, you have to lie a meeting
对了，您先躺会吧
To, you lie a meeting first
回皇上，李总管还在点收礼物
Return to emperor, manager Lee is ordering to accept a gift
说马上就来
Say coming right away
不像话，真不像话
Too ridiculous, true too ridiculous
这么多王公大臣等他一个人
So many dukes and high ministerses wait his a person
算什么？
Calculate what?
（董云伟饰太监）
(Dong Yun Wei decorates eunuch)
老叔
Old uncle
皇上候了您老半天
The emperor waited your old along while
不见您到，他发了好大脾气
Disappear you arrive, he delivered a very great temper
现在回养心殿去了
Return to cultivate mental calm a palace to go now
我看您越来越张狂了
I see you more and more insolent
皇上不要发作罢
The emperor doesn't want to deliver to forget about it
太不像话了，无妨用用家法
Be getting more beyond the limit, the no harm is used domestic discipline
家法？去找他来
Domestic discipline?Seek he comes
喳
Zha
老叔
Old uncle
皇上，奴才该死...
Your Majesty, the slave damns...
你知道就好了
You know good
奴才实在是张罗不过来
The slave really attends to needs not to come over
又忙着演礼，又忙着收礼儿
Be again busy in playing a gift, and then is busy in accepting gift son
奴才实在是...
Slave really BE...
这么说你是分身乏术了？
Say so that you were to divide time to lack Shu?
可是你就疏忽了
But you neglected
你不是老提家法家法的吗？
The domestic discipline that you aren't old to lift domestic discipline of?
皇上，奴才实在...
Your Majesty, the slave is true...
不要说了
Don't say
按家法，推出去打四十
Press the domestic discipline, release to beat 40
皇上
Emperor
皇上开恩吧
The emperor grand pardon
谁说也不成，太不像话了
Who say that don't become as well, beyond the limit
来呀
Come
喳
Zha
皇上
Emperor
推出去
Push to go out
喳
Zha
皇上
Emperor
快点
Hurry
皇上...
Emperor...
皇上，恐怕...
Your Majesty, perhaps...
这一来，事情更大
In this way, the affair is larger
大就大
Big big
快，慢了就来不及了
Quickly, slow too late
皇上
Emperor
他小人，不知怎么报复皇上呢
His mean person don't know how to make reprisals an emperor
要是给太后知道，这事...
If know for queen mother, this matter...
打了再说
Beat to say again
皇上，打过了
Your Majesty once beats
让他进来
Let him come in
今天是头一遭
Today is a first time
你别以为皇上好欺侮
You don't think that the emperor likes to humiliate
皇上
Emperor
我问你
I ask you
以后你还敢胡作非为假传圣旨吗？
You will dare to also act wildly in defiance of the law or public opinion hereafter does the leave spread Imperial decree?
皇上，奴才再也不敢了
Your Majesty, the slave doesn't dare any further
皇上，老佛爷有懿旨
Your Majesty, the old Buddha Ye has a Yi aim
让您慢点惩罚总管
Let you slowly punishment manager
他老人家来问明白了再说
He old man's house to find out white again say
他老人家说话就到了
His old man's house talked to is
已经打过了
Have already beaten
打过了？
Have ever beaten?
李总管，您到闼闼房歇会儿吧
Manager Lee, you arrive the Ta Ta building Xie meeting son
老叔
Old uncle
到闼闼房，我给您打两个鸡蛋
Arrive the building of Ta Ta, I beat two eggs for you
用鸡蛋即刻给您揉揉
The using an egg instant rubs for you
太后老佛爷驾到
The queen mother old Buddha Ye drives
亲爸爸
In person father
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
哥哥...
Elder brother...
亲爸爸
In person father
不用亲爸爸，干爸爸的
Need not close father does father
是怎么回事？
Is what is the row?
今天演礼
Play a gift today
王公大臣等了他一个下午
The dukes and high ministers waited him for an afternoon
您传旨来的时候
You spread the time that the aim comes
已经打过了
Have already beaten
打就打了吧
Beat and then beat
亲爸爸
In person father
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
奴才忙着演礼，又忙着收礼儿
The slave is busy in playing a gift, is busy in accepting gift son again
奴才忙得脚都朝了天了
The slave is busy feet all dynasty sky
奴才从今儿一大早到现在
Slave from now son in early morning till now
连口水都没有喝...
Even the salivas didn't drink...
活该
What a suck
谁叫你一天到晚演礼、收礼儿的
Who call you to all day play a gift and accept gift son
皇上这边的事一点也不问
The business of emperor's this place at 1:00 also not ask
老佛爷，奴才...
Old Buddha Ye, slave...
不要说了
Don't say
看见你就不顺眼
See you with a revolting feeling
来呀
Come
喳
Zha
把他抬出去
Carry it out him
喳
Zha
哥哥
Elder brother
看伤了筋骨没有？
See have already harmed physique?
来人，传太医进来给他瞧瞧
Bearer spreads to cure to come in too much to his lo lo
算了，死了又值几个大子？
Calculate, died and be worth how many big sons?
你哭什么？
What do you cry?
猫哭耗子假慈悲
The cat cries a mouse to pretend to be kind
都给我滚出去
All roll for me to go out
是
BE
亲爸爸，今天的事我实在...
In person father, today's business I am true...
对，你罚得很对
To, you punish very a rightness
我还说什么
I still say what
老佛爷，您别为这事生气了
Old Buddha Ye, you don't be this matter angry
我什么时候生气来着
I when angry come
皇上这样敢做敢为
The emperor dares to do like this dare be
我高兴还高兴不过来呢
I am happy to return happy however come
太后，今天...
Queen mother, today...
没你们的事了
Have no your businesses
你们在外面歇会儿
You at outside Xie meeting son
我跟皇上有几句话说
I have a few words to say with emperor
太后，今天这个事...
Queen mother, today this matter...
六爷这么大年纪了，还不辞劳苦
Six Yes so big ages, also not the Ci is hard working
您先回去吧
You return to first
是
BE
你是搁不得我的人哪
You is put not get I of person which
还是非找点丧气不可？
Or don't  seek to order frustrated can not?
打什么时候，我就说
Dozen when, I say
十月，十月我要图个吉利儿
In October, I want diagram in October lucky son
今儿大初一的，你就跟我找别扭
The son is big now beginning a, you seek with me pout
亲爸爸
In person father
你是不是故意跟我作对？
Do you intentionally set against with me?
亲爸爸，您可知道朝鲜的驻军
In person father, you know the garrison forces of Korea
已经退到鸭绿江边了
Have already backed the duck green river's side
我们的关外已经危在旦夕...
Our passes outside have already might fall at any moment...
你以为我不知道？
Do you think that I don't know?
那不能不办
That can not not do
要办应该先办你
Wanting to do should do you first
你不领着头
You don't get a head
左说打仗，右说打仗的
Left say that fight, right say fighting
我们会丢这么多地方
We will throw so many places
亲爸爸
In person father
你还有脸罚别人
You still have a face to punish other people
我还没罚你呢
Haven't I punished you
亲爸爸，我...
In person father, I...
你说，你认错儿不认错？
Do you say that you admit mistake son not to admit mistake?
说！
Say!
认错
Admit mistake
明白了吗？
Be getting more understand?
明白了
Understand
下了戏就到这儿来
Descended the drama is to come here
是
BE
我会想法子把她引来
My meeting viewpoint son is led her
你就上前干你的事
You come forward to do you of matter
不要问她是谁
Don't ask she is who
是（田青饰程月楼）
BE(the farmland green decoration distance month building)
就这么办了
Do so
喳
Zha
李总管不在这
Manager Lee not is here
是不是在听戏
BE is not going to opera
也没有
Also have no
真是
Be really
李总管说，您到了，谁也别见
Manager Lee says that you arrived, who don't also see
先到乐寿堂歇会儿，他就到
Arrive joy life hall first Xie meeting son, he is
他在哪儿？
Where is he ?
在清宴舫
In the pure Yan Fang
好
Good
皇后
Empress
你看
You see
就是他程月楼
Is his distance month building
瞧她美得那个相，心花都开了
Lo she is beautiful that mutually, the heart flowers all opened
翁师傅
Teacher Weng
老佛爷听说李伯爷来了
The old Buddha Ye hears that Li Bo2 Ye came
连戏都不听了，到乐寿堂去了
Even none of dramas listenned to and had already arrived joy life hall to go
皇上一定还蒙在鼓里
The emperor definitely still kepts in the dark
你赶快到乐寿堂去一趟
You at once arrive joy life hall to 1
想办法请皇上出来
Think the way invite an emperor to come out
是
BE
少喝酒啊
Little drink
知道了
Know
都走了
All walk
实说吧，打得怎么样？
Actually say and beat how?
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
我装聋卖傻可以
I pack deaf sell silly can
可是你们不该真瞒着我
But you don't should really deceive me
老佛爷，赶明儿个再说吧
Old Buddha Ye rushes through tomorrow to say again
今儿个是您万寿之日
The son is you now the day of ten thousand lifes
大喜的日子，您问这个干什么？
The day of exultation, what do you ask this stem?
没关系
Don't relate to
说实话，说真话，才是孝敬我
Tell the truth, say true words, be show filial obedience me
告诉我，打得怎么样？
Tell me, beat how?
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
没关系，告诉我
It doesn't matter and tell me
你没赶来参加大典
You didn't rush through to take part in big Dian
一定是情势紧急，是不是？
Must be that the situation is urgent, is be not?
老佛爷，今儿个大好的日子
Old Buddha Ye, now son greatly nice day
何必找别扭呢？
Why the need for seek pout?
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
今天举国都在放声大赦
Today the whole country all at put a general amnesty
庆祝盛典
Celebrate prosperous Dian
关于打仗的事...
Concerning the matter for fighting...
说好了，不管是什么日子
Say good, ignore is what day
我不能闷在葫芦里
I not the ability is stuffy in the bottle gourd
老佛爷，臣罪该万死
Old Buddha Ye, minister offense should ten thousand die
说
Say
已经打到天津了
Have already beaten Tienjin
祝寿赐宴，都打到京畿了
Wish a life to grant Yan, all beat city Ji
还装不知道，怎么得了
Also pack not to know, how will all this end
着急有什么用，总要想办法对付
The get excited has what use, always need to think the way deals with
我一定要见李鸿章
I must see Li Hong Zhang
怕见不着吧
Afraid could not see
李总管跟他寸步不离
Manager Lee and he is closely
不管，你去找找看
No matter, you look for it
喳
Zha
珍主子，今儿晚上人多事乱
Jean main son, now evening of son person's many matters disorderly
您可别乱遛跶
You don't disorderly Liu 跶
为什么？
Why?
怕什么？
Afraid of?
奴才是一句忠告
The slave is that one is advice
快去吧，真罗嗦
Quick go to, true bothersome
你看酒还没醒呐
You see the wine having not come to shout
奴才没有醉
The slave didn't inebriate
奴才心里明白
The slave knows it in heart
我先回去了
I returned to first
免得他们又说闲话
In case they say gossip again
管他们呢
Take care of them
不，我们犯不上
Not, we aren't worthwhile
你陪陪我
You go along with me
咱们好久没见了
We didn't see for a long time
你知道吗？我一直在想你
Do you know?I always at miss you
皇上吉祥
Emperor's good luck
都起来吧
All get up
谢皇上
Thank an emperor
原来你在这儿
Originally you are here
刚才老佛爷还一直在问你呢
Just old Buddha Ye still always at ask you
是吗？
BE?
李大姐
Elder sister Lee
皇上请您
The emperor invites you
叫我？
Call me?
这倒新鲜呐
This pours fresh shout
珍主儿
Jean main son
我以为是找我，原来还是找你
My thinking is to seek me and originally still seek you
找我？
Seek me?
皇上跟端王爷他们在说话呢
Emperor with carry Wang Ye at talk
叫我告诉你在清宴舫候驾
Call me to tell you to wait for your arrival in the pure Yan Fang
他说几句话就到
He speaks a few lines to is
清宴舫？
Pure Yan Fang?
恭请
Please respectfullly
寿星老佛爷慈禧端佑
The birthday person old Buddha Ye Ci Xi carries to bless
康毅昭豫
The Kang Yi Zhao Yu
庄诚寿恭
Chuang truly the life is respectful
钦献皇太后赐晚宴
The Qin dedicates empress dowager to grant a dinner
恭祝皇太后福如东海寿比南山
Wish empress dowager blessing respectfullly to compare south mountain such as life in East China Sea
万岁、万岁、万万岁
Long live, long live, ten thousand long live
你
You
放开我
Release me
来人哪...
Which is bearer...
放开我
Release me
不好了，来人哪
Not like, bearer which
快点来人哪
Hurry a bearer where
不好了，那边有人呐
Not like, there someone shout
快点
Hurry
放手
Let go
是珍贵妃叫我来的...
It is a precious imperial concubine to call me to come...
吓着了吧？别怕...
Frightenned?Don't fear...
皇上
Emperor
慢着
Slow
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
怎么回事？
What is the row?
我...
I...
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
吓死我了，有个野人哪
Frighten to death me, have a savage country people which
什么？
What?
程月楼
The distance month building
怎么回事？
What is the row?
你跟珍贵妃是什么回事？
Your heel precious imperial concubine is what return to matter?
珍贵妃原来跟我很有交情
The precious imperial concubine originally has much of friendship with me
前几天，她还跟我要过照片呢
A few days ago, did she still once want photograph with me
刚才下了戏珍贵妃叫人约我
Just descended drama the precious imperial concubine call person invite I
叫我混进清宴舫子里敘敘
Call me to mix into pure Yan Fang son inside 敘敘
你胡说
Your blah
住口，推下去
Shut up, push next go to
打
Beat
喳
Zha
我冤枉...
I wrong...
珍贵妃你这没良心的珍贵妃
Precious imperial concubine your this conscienceless precious imperial concubine
这回你可害苦了我了，珍贵妃
This time you can harm to gave me a hard time, precious imperial concubine
你好没良心啊，我冤枉啊
You are very conscienceless, I wrong
好撒野呀
Act boorishly so much
也不管今儿是什么日子
It is what day to also ignore now son
珍贵妃，你受委屈了吧
Precious imperial concubine, you are discommoded
快起来吧
Get up quickly
慢着
Slow
到底是怎么回事？
Exactly and what is the row?
老佛爷，我什么都不知道
Old Buddha Ye, I don't know anything
装糊涂！他怎么不说别人呢？
Packing is careless!How doesn't he say other people?
老佛爷，我...
Old Buddha Ye, I...
我问你，黑灯瞎火的
I ask you, the black light is blind fiery
你一个人到清宴舫干什么？
Does your a person arrive pure Yan Fang to do what?
我...
I...
老佛爷，你就别问了，反正是...
Old Buddha Ye, you don't ask, anyway BE...
我看你就不是好来头
I see you and then isn't a good position
说不说？不说掌嘴巴
Say not to say?Don't say slapping on the face Ba
老佛爷，我...
Old Buddha Ye, I...
你，你还委屈？
You, do you still discommode?
今儿我要图个顺序
Now son I want diagram in proper order
你偏给我找别扭
You are partial to seek pout for me
还有什么好说的，来人
Still have what say so much of, bearer
喳
Zha
推下去打
Push next beat
冤枉呀
Wrong
老佛爷，冤枉的
Old Buddha Ye wrongs
老佛爷，是冤枉的
Old Buddha Ye, is wrong
冤枉的
Wrong
老佛爷，珍主子是被人陷害的
Old Buddha Ye, Jean the main son is framed up
珍主子是冤枉的
The Jean main son is to wrong
冤枉的呀
Wrong
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
你喊什么冤？
What Yuan do you shout?
来点吉祥的好不好？
To order good luck of not very good?
李总管
Manager Lee
总管
Manager
押下去
Escort next go to
喳
Zha
老佛爷...
Old Buddha Ye...
用大刑
Use big Xing
冤枉啊，老佛爷
Wrong, old Buddha Ye
您被蒙在鼓里了
You were kepted in the dark
好人歹人您都分不清
Good man's bad people you can not distinguish
天下已经保不住了
The world has already canned not guarantee
天津都快丢了
Tienjin almost threw
您还被蒙在鼓里，我的老佛爷
Your returning is kepted in the dark, my old Buddha Ye
老佛爷，他们瞒着您啊老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye, they deceive you old Buddha Ye
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
天下都保不住了，老佛爷
The worlds all could not guaranteed, old Buddha Ye
你还发酒疯，推下去
You still behave ridiculously and push next go to
用重刑　打
Beat with the heavy Xing
冤枉啊老佛爷
Wrong old Buddha Ye
慢着
Slow
他是小孩子，多喝了两口
He is a child and drank two people more
念他平时没什么大差池
Read aloud his peacetime nothing important big mistake
饶了他吧！
Rao he!
喳
Zha
放开他
Release him
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
好了
Good
现在什么都揭穿了
Expose everything now
我在这儿装着笑脸、提着精神
I pack smiling face and lift spirit here
还不是打肿脸充胖子
Not just puff oneself up to one's own cost
既然纸里包不住火
Now that wrap not to live fire in paper
好，咱们就让它烧起来吧
Like, we let it burn
亲爸爸
In person father
对了，你是皇上
To, you are an emperor
现在娘娘、妃子、大小官员
Now empress, imperial concubine and big small fry
太监、宫女都在这儿
Eunuch, maid-in-waitings all here
你说吧！仗是你要打的
You say!The battle is that you want something to beat
现在打到天津了，你说怎么办？
Beat Tienjin now, do you say how to do?
珍妃是你自个儿选的
The Jean imperial concubine is that you choose from the son
如今出了这份丑
Now this is ugly
你说怎么办？
Do you say how to do?
我...
I...
亲爸爸，您，您说...
In person father, you, you say...
住口
Shut up
今天是我的好日子
Today is my nice day
亲爸爸
In person father
我错了
I am wrong
老佛爷，大好日子您呕什么气呢
Old Buddha Ye, greatly nice day your Ou what annoy
我愿意呀？
I would like to ah?
您往开处想吧
You go toward to open place to think
珍妃的事冤与不冤，你们去查啊
The Jean imperial concubine's business Yuan with not Yuan, you check
反正我说过
Anyway I once said
今儿这日子口，让我不痛快的
Now son this, make me not happy
老佛爷，求您一笑还求不过来呢
Old Buddha Ye, begs you a smile to still beg however come
谁那么大胆子敢呢
Who so bold son dare
珍贵妃的事过几天再说吧
The precious imperial concubine's business in a couple of days says again
您就不图个吉利
You not the diagram is lucky
也该有个忌讳呀
Should also have a taboo
还忌讳？越忌讳差越多
Still avoid as taboo?More avoid as taboo more many bad
就说打仗的事吧
Say that fight of matter
还有第二条道可走吗？
Can still having the second way walk?
如今晚儿只好做城下之盟了
The son has to do now night city under of alliance
是，亲爸爸
BE, in person father
我看你是不到黄河心不死
I see you be not to do arrive yellow river heart deathless
翁师傅，一共几条，你再念一遍
Teacher Weng, totally several, you read aloud 1 time again
是
BE
主要的几条是，一...
Mainly several BE, a...
中国承认朝鲜为完全独立自主之国
China admits that Korea is a completely independently independent country
二、割辽东半岛...
Two, mow Liaotung Peninsula...
台湾及附属诸岛...
Taiwan and subsidiary various island...
彭湖列岛
Archipelago in the Peng lake
三、赔款军费两万万两
Three, indemnity military expenses 20,0=2
听明白了没有？
Have already listenned to understand?
李鸿章已经在马关跟人画了押
Li Hong Zhang has already closed to draw to escort with others in the horse
现在就等着两国皇上
Wait two now country emperor
一批准，就正式换约
One approval formally exchanges the treaty
要是都没话，咱们可就认了
If all have no words, we can recognize
慢着...
Slow...
条款不是要两国的皇上批准吗？
Doesn't the item want the emperor of two countries to grant?
我看还是把皇上请出来
I see still please out emperor
好好地商量...
Well the company measures...
六爷，您怎么这么死心眼
Six Yes, you how so simple-minded
我不是跟您说过了
I am to once say with you
皇上不太舒坦，不便走动
The emperor isn't that at ease, the inconvenience takes a stroll
他要是能出来
If he can come out
这件事儿，还用我管吗？
This matter son also uses my tube?
他究竟是一国的主子
He is actually a main midland son
这么大的事他怎么可以不参与呢
So big matter does he how to not participate in
臣看也应该把皇上请出来商量
The minister sees to also please out the company to the emperor quantity
好吧
All right
我是怕皇上太劳累，病得又沉重
I am that the afraid emperor is too tired, disease again heavy
既然你们都这样说
Now that you all say like this
好吧！累就累吧
All right!Tired
你们就先下去，吃了饭再来
You descend first to go and had a meal again come
过来，这是你的好皇上
Come over, this good emperor who is you
你们不是一个多月没会了吗？
You aren't more than a months to have no meeting?
在这儿会会吧
At here meeting meeting
伺候他就像伺候病人一样
Wait upon he is like to wait upon a patient similar
忖度着时辰，摸摸他的头
Consider hour, touch his head
看看他发不发烧
See his hair not fever
再喂他点水喝
Feed again he orders water to drink
懂吗？
Understand?
懂
Understand
去
Go to
去，快去
Go, go quickly
是
BE
死相
The dead is mutually
坐下来
Sit down
手
Hand
慢着
Slow
人还没来呢
Hasn't the person come yet
就急得这样
Nasty get so
连材
Connect a material
喳
Zha
叫他们进来
Call them to come in
喳
Zha
王商
Wang Shang
喳
Zha
我告诉你
I tell you
要是给我露点口风
If give me dewdrop breeze
你心里明白
You know it in heart
喳
Zha
轻点儿
A little bit light son
算了罢，皇上躺着免了大礼吧
Calculated, the emperor lies to never mind a big gift
你们也都起来
You also all get up
谢老佛爷
Thank old Buddha Ye
给六爷看个坐儿
Make sat son
喳
Zha
皇上，皇上的病？
Your Majesty, the emperor's disease?
也摸不清是怎么回事
It is what is the row to also can not understand
反正太医天天进来开方子
Anyway and too cure to come in to open square son every day
怎么？皇上自个儿不能说话？
How?Can the emperor not talk from the son?
太医嘱咐的少开口
The little openings that cures to instruct too much
话多了伤神
The words are many mentally taxing
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
看皇上的气色还不坏
The complexion that sees an emperor returns pretty good
糟就糟在这儿
Bad here
大概是痨症吧
Probably is a Lao disease
病越沉重脸色愈好看
The disease more heavy facial expression is good-looking more
皇上合着眼，是不是睡着了？
The emperor matches to fix attention on, whether asleep?
就这么一天到晚昏迷不醒的
So all day the obfuscation don't come to
我们讲，他还听得见？
Do we speak that he still cans hear?
可以听得见
Can can hear
有时候也不知是心痛还是哪儿痛
It is a heartache to sometimes don't know as well or where painful
还哎哟哎哟的呢
Return Alas! Alas!
你听，说来就来了不是
You listen to, say to come right away be not
帮他翻个身
Turn over a body for him
我呢已经跟皇上谈过了
What about me have already talked over with emperor
他没什么主意
His nothing important idea
打开天窗说亮话
Open skylight to have frank talk
咱们只是一只纸糊的老虎
We are just a tiger of paper paste
老远的瞧着吓唬吓唬人还可以
From afar of the lo write scare a person can also
好，你们这一打
Like, you this
得，把纸老虎给捅穿了
Get, give° the paper tiger Tong to wear
现在想吓唬人也吓唬不住了
Want to scare a person to also scare not to live now
那还有什么说的
That still has what say
还不是人家说什么
Not just the somebody else says what
咱们就得是什么
We have to be what
人家要什么，咱们就得给什么
The somebody else wants what, we have to give what
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
这条款实在是太苛刻
This item is really a Ke to engrave too much
古今中外怕还没听过这样的条款
Now the thou is Chinese and Foreign to fear haven't listenned to item like this
割的地比他们本国的国土还要多
The ground mown than they of the native national territory still wants much
什么条款？
What item?
什么？
What?
皇上在问什么？
What is the emperor asking?
皇上在问什么条款
The emperor is asking what item
谁说的？
Who say?
没的事，皇上在说胡话
Matter of having no, emperor at say beard words
珍妃，摸摸他发不发烧
Jean imperial concubine, touches his hair not fever
是
BE
很烧
Burn very much
不该出来的
Should not come out
真是不该出来
Be really should not come out
为了国家皇上也就...
For the sake of the national emperor is also...
得了...不必说什么漂亮话了
Get...Go without saying what beautiful words
什么天下，什么国家
What world, what nation
我还不知道这条款苛刻吗
Don't I still know that this item Ke engraves
我还愿意把三岛都割给我们
I would like to also all mow three islands to us
赔我们四万万两哪
Compensate us 40,0=2 which
办得到吗？
Make it?
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
可不可以重新议和？
Can afresh argument and?
谁去？你去？
Who go?Do you go?
那时候李鸿章拉你去你都不去
Li Hong Zhang pulled at that time you went to you not to go
要不然我们整兵再战
Otherwise our whole soldier fight again
对，再战
To, fight again
我们整兵再战
Our whole soldier fights again
怎么啦，皇上？
How, emperor?
按住他
Press down him
是
BE
皇上
Emperor
再战
Fight again
皇上
Emperor
再战
Fight again
皇上
Emperor
再战...
Fight again...
我看皇上的病真不轻
I see the emperor's disease really not light
可不是嘛
Be not
我没病...
I didn't disease...
胡说
Blah
亲爸爸，我好了
In person father, I liked
好了也给我躺着会儿
Like also lie meeting son for me
给他口水喝
Give him the saliva to drink
是
BE
我不喝
I don't drink
我不渴
I not thirst
今儿皇上的病可重得多了
The son emperor's disease can weigh much now
你还好意思说整兵再战
You return not bashful say the whole soldier again fight
要不然日本东北有两个大国
Otherwise the Japanese northeast has two big countries
一个叫缅甸，一个叫交趾
One calls Burma, 1 calls hand over a toe
地方比日本大好几倍
Place than big quite a few in Japan is doubly
日本怕他们比怕老虎还怕
Japan is afraid they than afraid the tiger still fear
要是能派遣一位能说会道的大臣
If can send an a good talker big minister
跟他们拉拢拉拢，那...
Draw together with them, that...
越说越不像话了
More saying is more too ridiculous
亲爸爸，我...
In person father, I...
别着急，好好养病
Don't become nervous, convalesce well
听听他们有什么办法
Listen to them having what way
臣倒有个最省事的不求人的招儿
The minister pours to have to simplify matters most not to ask others for help of recruit son
我们训练一批新的巴图鲁
We train new Ba Tu Lu
用新家伙...
Use new guy...
长竹竿，日本倭子腿短手短
Long bamboo pole, the Japanese Wo son leg short hand is short
让他接不上手
Let him can not connect a hand
我们就把他们的乌球都给弄下来
We their black balls all to make down
怎么啦？
How?
大清不亡，实无天理！！
Big pure not Wu, actually have no nature's law!!
你疯了，什么话？
You went crazy, what rubbish?
亲爸爸
In person father
我实在躺不住了
I really lie not to live
你让我说几句，好不好？
You make me speak a few lines, not very good?
你身子要紧
Your body is important
又要说什么胡话
Want to say again what beard words
亲爸爸，他们说的才是胡话
In person father, what they say is beard words
亲爸爸，我看事已至此
In person father, I see matter already to this
还是把...
Or chase...
康有为，康有为那些举人
The Kang is capable, the Kang is capable those raise a person
公车上书的意思是...
Book of bus of meaning BE...
你先歇会吧
You first Xie meeting
亲爸爸
In person father
听见没有？
Have been already heard?
不要这样...
Don't so...
皇上他年轻又在病着
Emperor's some time lightly again at get sick
皇上既然提了
The emperor since lifted
他刚才提的是谁呀？
He just lifted of is who ah?
康有为，公车上书的事
The Kang is capable, the business of the bus last book
好吧，无论什么事
All right, regardless what matter
和和气气地商量商量
In a kind spirit the company measures a company quantity
康有为是谁？
Is the Kang capable to is who?
我听都没听说过嘛
I listen to have never heard
他们这些赶考的举子
They these rush through to test of raise son
还没做上官呢，就不安分
Haven't done an officer, not law-abiding
动不动就联名上书
On every occasion jointly last book
还能有什么好杂碎
Can also have what good giblets
亲爸爸
In person father
那一千多人联名上的万言书...
Those more than 1,000 persons are jointly last of ten thousand speech books...
没有你什么说的
Have no you what say
亲爸爸
In person father
你忘了你有病了？
You forgot are you getting sicker?
病，我是病了
Disease, I was to get sick
我没说没病
I didn't say didn't disease
病得很重
Badly sick
可是这么大的事
But so big matter
您不能不让我说
You can not not make me say
谁不让你说来着？
Who don't make you say to wear?
好像谁欺负你似的
Seem who humiliate you
算了...皇上还病着
Forget it...The emperor still gets sick
我是一个妇道，人家都欺侮我
I am a woman's proper conduct, the somebody elses all humiliate me
有什么不是都偏派在我头上
Have what be not be all partial to a parties on my head
我还不是为了你，为了祖宗
I not just for the sake of you, for the sake of ancestor
为了百姓，为了天下
For the sake of the common people, for the sake of world
早点太平，大家安生
Earlier peace, everyone Anne livings
我是一片苦心哪
I am with patience an one which
到了人家说我，你也说我
Arrived a somebody else to say me, you also said me
我这个委曲到那儿去说呀
I this injustice go there to say
您瞧您
Your lo you
老佛爷，您这是何苦呢
Old Buddha Ye, you is this why on earth
何苦呢？
Why on earth?
皇上生病，发烧说几句胡话
The emperor gets sick and get a fever to speak a few lines beard words
也是有之
Is also have it
您一向那么透亮
You are always so deeply bright
怎么一时慒懂了
How at that time the 慒 understood
生病说胡话，您何必往心里去呢
Get sick to say beard words, do you why the need for go toward in the mind
何必跟病人一般见识呢
Why the need for hold the same kind of view with patient
老佛爷，臣最信太上感应篇
Old Buddha Ye, minister most the letter respond an article too up
据臣之愚见
According to the my humble opinion of minister
什么事都是有个因果
What matters all have a cause and effect
因果都有个报应
The cause and effects all have a retribution
不是人力可以挽回的
Being not a manpower can save
今日事已至此
The matter has already gone to this today
不论什么条款
Whatever item
我们只好答应着
We have to promise
等我们把内部的
Wait we chase internal
洋章京祸害精
The ocean chapter disaster Jing in the city
大汉奸都扫除了
The big fellow was crafty to all sweep away
再说复仇的话
Say the words of vengeance again
对，现在先接受条款
To, accept item first now
将来给他一个翻脸不认账
Will give him one to turn over a face to recognize Zhang not in the future
对的，这个话对极了
Rightness of, this words are Right-o
总之，老佛爷
In fine, old Buddha Ye
臣等的意见一致都附会接受条款
The opinion that the minister waits all unanimously the false assumption accept item
老佛爷，您别难过了
Old Buddha Ye, you didn't be sad
他们爷们都说接受条款了
They the Yes all said accepting item
皇上自然更无可无不可
Emperor nature more have no can all can
何必呕气呢
Why the need for feel enraged
反正都为的早点太平嘛
All anyway is of breakfast peace
老佛爷，这条款要是一签订
Old Buddha Ye, if this item a sign
失掉土地，失掉金银还算小事
Lose a land, lose gold and silver to return calculate small matter
最可怕的是失掉人心哪
The most terrible is to lose public which
全国的老百姓
The common people of whole country
看出这朝廷软弱无能
See this imperial government weak inability
无力保全他们的身家性命
Have no dint to keep intact their own life and family possessionses
那就可危险了，老佛爷
That can be getting more dangerous, old Buddha Ye
你这是什么意思？
You is this what mean?
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
南方各省正在闹革命党
Southern each province is making revolutionary party
打的旗号是推翻满清
The signal of beating is to overthrow Qing Dynasty
五族共和
Five clan republicans
喊的口语是：外患侵入，民不聊生
The vernacular speech of shouting is:The foreign invasion invades, the people find it hard to live on
您想这时候
You think by this time
这条款要是一签订
If this item a sign
老百姓岂不更要揭竿而起吗？
Does the common people not and more want to revolt but rise?
你是拿这个吓唬我
You are to take this to scare me
老佛爷，这不是吓唬
Old Buddha Ye, this not is scare
这是事实
This is the fact
最近...
Recent...
广东省革命党兴中会
Province revolutionary party in Guangdong interest medium meeting
夺取省城的事
Seize the business of saving the city
您不知道？
Don't you know?
固然有好多人就擒被捕
Surely a lot of persons submitting to capture is caught
但他们的领袖已经逃到澳门去了
But their leaders have already escaped to go to Macau
他们的党徒遍江南
Their party Tu time Chiang-Nan
他们是不会甘心的呀，老佛爷
They aren't pleased of ah, old Buddha Ye
那怕什么？
Is that afraid of?
我可以下道旨意加以防范
I can the next aim idea take into to guard against
把他们斩尽杀绝
Cut them to to the utmost kill to cut off
老佛爷，他们是斩不尽杀不绝的
Old Buddha Ye, they are to cut to not and to the utmost kill never-failing
那怎么办呢？
What to do then?
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
我知道了
I knew
你是跟他们有来往
You are to have friendly intercourse with them
故意把他们说的这么威风
Intentionally they say of so power and prestige
老佛爷，我...
Old Buddha Ye, I...
我这个人就是这个倔脾气
I am this obstinate temper
你说不行我偏要试巴试巴
You say not to go me to bent on having try Ba Shi Ba
老佛爷再说这条款一签订
The old Buddha Ye says this items again a sign
皇上头一个在老百姓的前面
The emperor first one is in the front of common people
就抬不起头来
Lift to not and at first come
皇上抬不起头来
The emperor lifts to not and at first come
他自己当然知道怎么下台了
He certainly knew how to resign by himself
给我少说两句吧
Say 2 less for me
我看你是越老越糊涂
I see you are more old more careless
只好先回老家去喝你的小米粥吧
Have to return to the millet congee that drinks you in the old house first
亲爸爸
In person father
我知道我不成
I know that I don't become
我没脸再当皇上
I am disgraced again be emperor
好，我让位，我一定让位
Like, I abdicate, I definitely abdicate
可是翁师傅他，别让他走吧
But teacher Weng, don't make him leave
你不放他走，就是你不肯让位
You don't put he walks, is that you Be not willing to abdicate
看你们这些君不君，臣不臣的
See you these gentleman not gentleman, minister not minister of
还有什么脸
Still how can
亲爸爸，我肯
In person father, I be willing to
您什么时候叫我让位
You when call me to abdicate
我立刻就让
I immediately let
我叫你让位？
Do I call you to abdicate?
不是你自个儿说的？
Isn't what you say from the son?
你没脸当皇上，要称病下台吗？
You are disgraced to be an emperor and on pretext of illness resign?
亲爸爸，我没有
In person father, I have no
没有？
Have no?
就算我有
Calculate I have
亲爸爸，我下台可以
In person father, I resign can
这议和的条款可不能认可啊
This argument and of the item can not approve
你...越说越斜了
You...More saying is more inclined
不是你自个儿说的
Isn't that you say from the son
你没有别的办法，只好签定条款
You don't have another way and have to sign item
亲爸爸，我？
In person father, I?
什么时候？我没有
When?I have no
你没有？
Do you have no?
我真的没有
I really have no
难道我睁着眼睛说瞎话？
Does my Zheng wear eyes to tell a tall tale?
你没有，没有？
You have no and have no?
你有没有？
Do you have?
有没有...
Have...
住手...
Stop...
住手！
Stop!
光绪爷
Guangxu Ye
你当了这么一个可怜的皇上啊
You wased the emperor of such a wretchedness
你这位皇太后
You this empress dowager
你是越来越霸道了
You were more and more a violent in action
什么事都独断独行
What matters all high-handed
文宗给我留下的遗诏
The text believes in leave for me of loose Zhao
叫我约束你
Call me to control you
我从来就没有用过
I have never used
今儿，今天我可要用一用啦
Now son, I can want to use today
文宗
The text believes in
我问你
I ask you
把祖宗三百年的天下断送了
Break ancestor 300 years of world to send
于你有什么好处？
Have in you what advantage?
我问你
I ask you
光绪帝是你自己立的皇上
The Guangxu emperor is the emperor whom you sign by yourself
你究竟是何居心啊，你？
You actually and with what evil intention, you?
他没有病你叫他装病
He doesn't have the disease you call him to pretend illness
他不肯签约，你逼着他签约
He isn't willing to make a contract, you make him make a contract
你真是上何以对祖宗
You be really top why to ancestor
下，何以对天下的臣民啊，你...
Next, why to the subjects of a ruler of world, you...
老祖宗
Old ancestor
皇上凭什么让位？
Emperor with what abdicate?
不让位
Don't abdicate
让位？
Abdicate?
咱们把皇亲贵戚
We kiss the expensive Qi to the emperor
近支的王公贝勒、福晋公主
The princes and dukes shell of the near Lei and blessing Jin princess
都请到先庙去
All please arrive first temple to go to
在文宗的陵前焚道表
Believe in in the text of before the Ling Fen way watch
反正我也是快入土的人了
Anyway I am quickly to bury of person
我拿这条老命我就跟她拼了
I take this old life I put together with her
闭住气，快扶他躺一躺
Hold breath, hand quickly he lie down
别结...
Don't knot...
躺一下怕什么？
Is lying down for a while afraid of?
使不得皇上，君臣总得有个分别
Will not do an emperor, the king and his ministers musts have a difference
这是您的御榻
This is your to resist Ta
那怎么办？
What to do then?
快点扶到王府去吧
Quickly hand Wang Fu to go
对啦，快扶到王府去吧
To, hand Wang Fu to go quickly
回到府里，您爱怎么躺就怎么躺
Return to a mansion inside, you love how lie how lie
您爱怎么骂就怎么骂
Your love how scold how scold
李总管，外面下着雨
Manager Lee, there is rain outside
这一出去风吹雨打的
This goes out wind blows and rain beats down
那恭王爷..
That respectful Wang Ye..
要你多嘴多舌的
Want you much more talkative glossal
快扶下去
Will hand quickly next go to
恭王爷...
Respectful Wang Ye...
皇上
Emperor
干你的，不要怕
Do you, don't fear
有我呢...干你的
Have me...Do you
老祖宗
Old ancestor
您回到了府里，好好的平平气
You returned to a mansion inside, thoroughly so-so spirit
大大的睡它一觉，请吧
Consumedly sleep once it feel and please
恭王爷
Respectful Wang Ye
皇上
Emperor
我的皇上
My emperor
难道您这一辈子
You this lifetime
再见不到恭亲王爷了
Could not see respectful prince Ye again
请您放手吧
Please let go
请吧
Please
这个是我们的家务事
This is our household choreses
用不着你这个份外人来操这份心
Have no call to your this outsider to hold this heart
我这个人呢，就是这份倔脾气
What about me, is this obstinate temper
吃软不吃硬
Open to persuasion but not to coercion
什么来，拿什么挡
What come, take what block
别看我们吵，我们是一家子
Don't see us noisy, we are a son
你呢，岁数也不小了
What about you, the age wasn't young either
辛苦了这么些年
Pain so some years
明儿一早，回家养老去吧
The tomorrow goes home to retire to enjoy life to go to early in the morning
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
不必说什么了
Go without saying what
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
臣只有一个愿望
The minister only has wishes
什么？
What?
臣愿在临行之前
The minister wishes before facing to go
跟皇上再恳谈一次
Heel emperor again the Ken talk once
你还想挑唆他？算了吧
Do you still want to instigate him?Forget it
亲爸爸
In person father
咱们爷儿俩，本来挺好的
Our Ye son a pair, original quite good
都是他们挑唆坏了的
All is that they instigated to break down
亲爸爸
In person father
你就答应他的这个请求吧
You promise his claim
不行
Don't go
你现在可以回去了
You can return to now
是
BE
臣跟您拜别了
The minister paid a farewell called with you
皇上
Emperor
臣也跟你拜别
The minister also pays a farewell calls with you
愿您万岁万岁万万岁
Wish you long live long live ten thousand long live
还不谢谢翁师傅这么多年的教导
Still don't thank teacher Weng so several years of guidance
翁师傅，今生今世
Teacher Weng, this present life present life
能不能再见？
Can you see again?
瞧瞧成什么体统？
What convention does the lo lo become?
翁师傅，快请吧
Teacher Weng please quickly
祝您一帆风顺、一路平安
Wishing you is Bon voyage, a pleasant journey
请吧
Please
各位大人，有请了
Each adult has already pleased
这一仗呢，总算闹完了
What about this battle and finished making on the whole
也没什么大不了的事儿了
Also no big deal matter son
我呐，也实在上了年纪
I shout and also really ascended age
懒得再操这份心
Lazy must hold this heart again
我们娘们儿马上到颐和园去
We the Niangs the son go to Summer Palace right away
朝廷的事呢，以后都交给你了
What about the matter of imperial government, hereafter all hand over to you
我再也不管了
I ignored any further
亲爸爸
In person father
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
现在正是要紧的结股眼儿上
Now is exactly important knot eye son top
什么事都悬在这里，您怎么能走呢？
What matters all hang here, how can you walk?
你怎么又插嘴了？说了不改
How did you interrupt again?Said not to change
这孩子
This kid
喳，奴才忘了
Zha, the slave forgot
皇上还是您自己说吧
Emperor still you say by yourself
亲爸爸，您是先别走
In person father, you are to don't walk first
这一仗到底怎么完的怎么了的
This battle how exactly finish how of
我一点都不接头
I at 1:00 all not deal with contact
您还是...
You be still...
我都说了不管了
I have already said ignoring
还不知道我的脾气？
Still don't know my temper?
说不管就不管，什么都不管
Say that ignore and then ignore, what all ignore
亲爸爸，您这一走留下我一个人
In person father, you this walks to leave my a person
恭亲王爷不会再上朝了
The respectful prince Ye can't ascend a dynasty again
翁同禾、李鸿章
Weng together grain, Li Hong Zhang
都受命告老还乡了
All accept order to tell old return to home
我一个人能干什么？
I one personal ability what?
怎么会是一个人呢？
How can is a person?
我已经都给你安排好了
I already all give you arrangement like
翁同禾的缺呢由刚毅补上
Does Weng and grain lack is made up deficiencies by the toughness
刚毅
Resolute and firm
皇上多栽培
The emperor much educates
李鸿章的事由荣禄接管
Li Hong Zhang's origin of matter glory Lu takes over
还有端郡王戴漪、徐桐老先生
Still have already carried Wang Dai Yi of the county, Mr. Xu Tong Lao
他们都是你的好帮手
All of them are you of good assistant
皇上要重用你们了
The emperor wanted to weigh to use you
还不过来谢恩
Return however to thank for favor
喳
Zha
谢皇上
Thank an emperor
好了，现在什么都给你弄周全了
Like, now what all make for you thoughtful
没有我什么事了，咱们也该走了
Have no me what matter, we should also walk
就走，老佛爷？
Walk, old Buddha Ye?
皇上
Emperor
皇上您说话呀
The emperor talks
把老佛爷这一放走
Old Buddha Ye this releases
那可就什么事都完了
That can what matters all over
皇上您说话呀
The emperor talks
连材，你在嘀咕什么呢？
Connect a material, what are you whispering?
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
您别走吧
You don't leave
连材
Connect a material
什么？
What?
把李伯爷叫回来恭亲王请进来
Call Li Bo2 Ye to come back respectful prince to please to come in
翁师傅也叫回来
Teacher Weng also calls back
再好好商量、商量
Again the very good company measures, company quantity
有什么说不通的呢
Have what say impassability
您这一走他们爷儿们也都走了
You this walks their Ye the son also all walked
就留皇上一个人
Stay a person of emperor
这算怎么档子事呢，我的老佛爷
This calculates how file son matter, my old Buddha Ye
你哪来的这么多话？
You which come of so many words?
老佛爷，奴才话多着呢
Old Buddha Ye, do the slave words much wear
老想跟您说又怕记不清楚
Old want to say and fear to can not remember clearly Chu with you
我还写了一个条陈呢
Did I still write Chen
条陈？
Chen?
你还有条陈？
Do you still have Chen?
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
奴才知道您疼我，才这么大胆子
The slave knows you are painful I, just so big courage
奴才也知道您疼皇上
The slave also knows your painful emperor
可是有歹人从中挑拨
But have bad people from in provocation
才弄得您跟皇上不和美
Just make you heel emperor at enmity with beautiful
老佛爷，皇上究竟是皇上
Old Buddha Ye, the emperor is actually an emperor
他究竟年轻
He is actually young
有看不透的地方您给指点
Have the place to see not and deeply you give to point out
有看错的地方您给纠正
Visited a wrong place, you gave to rectify
就算有什么不是
Have on the whole what be not
您还能包涵不了吗？
Could you also can not forgive?
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
现在大难临头，您再不给皇上作主
Big difficult happen now, you don't make the decision for emperor again
谁来给皇上作主
Who come to make the decision for emperor
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
皇上开口闭口地叫您亲爸爸
Emperor's openings shuts up ground to call your close father
他不算不孝顺您
He doesn't calculate not filial agreeable you
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
您不要听歹人的话
You don't want to listen to the words of bad people
您开恩吧！老佛爷
You grand pardon!Old Buddha Ye
好啊！
Good!
这么大点的毛孩子
The hair kid who so greatly orders
倒教训起我来了
Pour to start to teach I came
老佛爷，奴才不敢
Old Buddha Ye, the slave doesn't dare
我问你
I ask you
这番话是哪个教给你说的？
This time words is which teach to say for you?
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
这是奴才从心坎儿里头挖出来的
This is the slave the inside dig out from the bosom son
原来是孝顺我？
BE show filial obedience me?
这么一说
So a say
这些年来我倒没白疼你呀
These in the last years I pour to have no white painful you ah
老佛爷，您别见怪
Old Buddha Ye, you don't be offended
奴才是有什么说什么
What does slave be to have to say what
直言无隐
Keep speech have no concealed
直言无隐？
Keep speech have no concealed?
我看你是不识抬举
I see you is to not worth
亲爸爸
In person father
一个个的都被我惯坏了
A s were all spoiled by me
连小猫小狗都想当家
Even the kitty puppies all want to take charge of
还有天地、上下、老少、尊卑吗
Still have world, top and bottom, old little and high and low
亲爸爸，他小孩子顺嘴乱说的
In person father, his child is smooth to blather
您别生气了
You don't get angry
打发他出去
Beat to deliver he goes out
要不把他轰出宫去算了
Want not to bomb a temple to him and calculate
不能这么算
Not ability so calculate
他一定是受什么人指使
He must be be subjected to what person direct
他以为我疼他，就不会怎么样他
He thinks I am painful he, how can't he
疼是疼，要是招上我的火儿来
Painful is painful, if recruit to ascend my fire son to come
得了，亲爸爸
Get, in person father
你给他讲什么情？
What feeling do you speak for him?
不行，我一定要问，还有这折子
Don't go, I must ask and also have this to fold son
是谁指使你写的？
BE who direct what you write?
老佛爷，您可别想拧了
Old Buddha Ye, don't you ever think Ning
皇天在上
The sky of the emperor is in the top
这折子要不是奴才自个儿写的
This folds son if not that the slave writes from the son
奴才
Slave
怎么样？还想撒野？
How?Still want to act boorishly?
自个儿写的？我就不信
Write from the son?I don't believe
念一遍给我听听
The reading aloud 1 time lets me listens to
喳
Zha
请太后不要独揽政权
Ask don't only Lan political power
请废颐和园还宫办事
Please discard Summer Palace to return a temple to handle affairs
请免修铁路
Please don't need to fix a railroad
请免革李鸿章的职
Please don't need the Ge Li Hong Zhang's job
请续修战备，跟日本再打
Please continuously fix a war preparedness and beat again with Japan
皇上无子嗣
The emperor has no progeny
请择天下之贤者立为皇太子
Please sign for the prince imperial
请太后
Please queen mother
得了...不伦不类，白字连篇
Get...Indescribable, the incorrect character connects article
又念得这么熟，倒像你自个儿写的
Read aloud so familiarly again, pour to be like you to write from the son
老佛爷，本来是奴才自己写的
The old Buddha Ye was originally a slave to write by himself/herself
不管是不是你自己写的
No matter is isn't that you write by yourself
你可知道祖宗的家法
You know the domestic discipline of ancestor
内监不准干预政事吗？
Inside does the Jian prohibit intervention politics?
奴才知道
The slave knows
可是事有缓急
But the matter is slowly nasty
就不敢拘于成例了
Don't dare the Ju was at the precedents
你不知道这是死罪吗？
You don't know this is a capital crime?
奴才知道
The slave knows
忠臣不怕死，怕死不忠臣
The loyal minister isn't afraid of dead and afraid of death loyal minister not
这条陈是奴才拼死命而上的
This Chen is a slave to put together to die a life but top
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
按祖宗家法，没什么说的了
Press the ancestor domestic discipline, the nothing important says of
疼我是疼，让我疼，我才疼
Painful I am painful, make me painful, I am just painful
不让我疼，我疼什么？
Don't make me painful, what am I painful?
既然如此，可别怪我太忍心
Since it is so, don't blame me too unfeeling
亲爸爸
In person father
还有什么说的？
Still have what say?
是
BE
来人哪
Which is bearer
喳
Zha
押下去
Escort next go to
是
BE
老佛爷，良药苦口啊
Old Buddha Ye, the good medicine is bitter in taste
奴才是一片忠心才说这个话
The slave is just an one loyal to say this words
老佛爷
Old Buddha Ye
您就算不为天下社稷打算
You don't for the world nation calculate to intend
难道您也不为自己想一想？
Aren't you for yourself either to consider?
奴才一死事小
Slave one dead matter is small
可是这天下...
But this world...
得了吧，连材
Get, connect a material
小小年纪，你还天下天下的
Small age, you return world world
这就是你小子的修因结果
This is your boy to fix because of result
有什么？
What?
好汉子，大丈夫，光荣的
Good brave fellow son, gentleman, glorious
大丈夫
Gentleman
你高寿啊？
You tall life?
十八
十八岁的大丈夫，别哭哇
18-year-old gentleman don't cry
不哭就不哭
Don't cry not to cry
你是贼胆子
You are thief's courage
我是忠心赤胆
I am a red loyal Dan
你忠心？
Your loyal?
你忘了，你不是说，连材有天良
You forgot, you not is say and connect a material to have conscience
你的天良呢？
You of conscience?
这就是我的天良
This is my conscience
我有天良我才上条陈
I have the conscience my just last Chen
我要是黑了良心
If I am black conscience
我才像你
I am just like you
押下去
Escort next go to
慢着
Slow
奴才伺候皇上、老佛爷一场
The slave waits upon emperor and old Buddha Ye 1
让奴才带着这口气
Make the slave taken this tone
跟老佛爷、皇上
The heel old Buddha Ye and emperor
告个永别
Tell to part forever
大清光绪二十一年
Greatly clear out a clue for 21 years
公元一八九五年
1895 A.D.
马关条约签定
Ma Guan's treaty signs
WWW.52HALFCD.COM
时代影视论坛 荣誉出品
谢谢收看！再见